hello and welcome everyone
it is june 13th 2022 and we're here in
acting lab guest stream number 23.1
with maxwell and dalton we're talking
about rebooting the free energy
principle literature and their recent
publication
so i'll pass it to the two of you to
provide just an initial introduction and
some context for the paper before we
jump into some specific parts
maxwell first
cool my name is maxwell ramstad
i'm the director of research at the
versus research lab
where we specialize in probabilistic
approaches to
artificial intelligence
um
and of late most of my research has been
on the physics foundations of the free
energy principle
and yeah very
very much looking forward to having this
conversation
awesome and dalton
sure um okay well i'm dalton uh i'm a
mathematician and a physicist
um
so right now i'm i'm uh at stony brook
university in new york i'm also at the
uh versus lab where we're doing some
work on the free energy principle right
now my research interests are about
formal approaches to biological physics
and mathematical foundations of complex
systems and these kinds of questions one
of the most interesting frameworks in
this sphere is the free energy principle
and that's uh how i've gotten involved
in this literature
awesome
so maybe in the same order
what brought us to this paper what was
the gap that this paper stepped into and
how did this team arise around the paper
and i'll bring it up on the screen as
well
it's a good question
um
well i i think the paper does a bunch of
different things um the first i mean
we've presented this as rebooting the
free energy principle literature um
i think uh
yeah over the last
it's been almost two decades now since
uh the fep has been a thing uh i think
the first paper was circa 2005 ish
and the
framework or the the field of study that
has emerged around the free energy
principle has
changed a lot over the last two decades
in no small part
in terms of the self-understanding that
we have
as a community of practitioners working
with these techniques
and i mean as dalton
pointed out a while back
i think the last time that really
the fep literature had been surveyed
in a systematic fashion to kind of
present where we were at uh where we
where we are currently like the state of
the art it was probably carl's uh
monograph from 2019 january 2019 um i
mean you know
both of you were part of this
international physics reading group that
we had uh this was not this is not a
simple
uh piece to read and uh
yeah since then um there hasn't really
been uh
basically a summary of where the
literature is so on the one hand we were
aiming to uh
reboot the literature
uh
to
to basically summarize uh the ways that
the free energy principle had been
applied uh in the literature
and uh
to also present a lot of the uh progress
that had been made over the last three
years a lot of which is due to uh dalton
so i think that segues nicely into the
dalton
well too generous by far as usual but uh
yeah so um maxwell raises a good point
that there uh hasn't been
really
an effort
to tie together all the different
threads since probably 2019
and uh
one of the reasons why
i mean that's
that's a long time but it's not overly
long however
in the last couple of years there have
been some pretty serious advances in the
state of the mathematics and the physics
behind the free energy principle so
now you know
three years later we're in 2022 it's not
a long time but nevertheless there have
been big developments that really
beg this kind of a survey to be done
and so that was one of the aims at least
of the paper was to draw together all
the different threads to unify them make
them a bit more cohesive
and and present
the free energy principle as we're
conceptualizing it today in a very top
to bottom fashion
so before we jump into the sections and
the arguments and the claims in the
paper which i'm sure will cover a lot of
these updates
i'd just love to hear
what is the free energy principle
what is active inference and how are
they related
i mean i i guess in the most general
sense the free energy principle
is a statement that says that we can
understand the the dynamics of
self-organizing systems as following um
a path of least surprisal in the most
general sense
and then in that context uh it's good
that you ask the question i think that
there are at least two
uses of the term active inference in the
literature
um the one that i've tended to use is a
very broad sense which is just like
active inference is specifying a path of
least action
um for what are called autonomous states
so like the active and internal states
of uh systems that can that are
considered things under the free energy
formulation
active inference has also been used to
refer to uh a class of specific
partially observable markov decision
process models um that have been
deployed and you know most of the
implement in silico implementations of
the free energy principle rely on these
i think this has led to a little bit of
confusion
in that you know when folks say
active inference is a general theory uh
it's able to account for
self-organization that they're not talk
they're not saying this specific class
of pond vp models is effectively you
know repurposable for everything um so
yeah i i would say that
this is
the first sense that i outlined is the
sense in which we say that active
inference is a corollary of the free
energy principle um
and yeah i mean in its most general form
the free energy principle is just a
statement uh
an alternative statement or restatement
of the principle of stationary action
where the action is defined as a
surprisal
in effect
great dalton same questions to you
yeah i think um maxwell pretty much um
covered it
uh so as i mentioned you know my
background is actually not in the free
energy principle not originally and it's
not even in
machine learning
uh so i've come at this literature with
a bit of a different um set of
ideas and traditions and tools
and so as a result i can't really talk
about active inference and i'm not
totally familiar with it
but i can talk about the free energy
principle um at length i'll try to be
brief
um so to me the the free energy
principle is a statement that
random dynamical systems
uh do on average
unsurprising things
and and it's a very simple statement all
it means is that
if you have a random dynamical system
and it's trying to
get to some place in state space
that is not surprising to it
so some preferred region of state space
maybe a particular phenotype maybe a
particular
morphological blueprint something like
this
the free energy principle is a statement
of
not only that that happens but also a
set of tools to model how that happens
how do systems get to these kinds of
attractors
and there's this very interesting way
in which
the
the getting to that attractor can be
read as inference
and this is where these all these
connections in literature appear to um
things like active inference you can
talk about how systems actually get
themselves to that attractor as a
perception an action problem and you can
model it using this very famous uh
variational free energy bound and you
can show okay when the system is
encoding some sort of belief about its
environment and about itself that when
it does this inference you have the
minimization of some upper bound on
surprisal so so the system is at least
doing
unsurprising things at the level of
you know it's not exceeding some kind of
intrinsic surprise
that's some of the early formulations
some of the more recent formulations
take it even further and you say the
surprising full stop of of some
trajectory of the system is going to be
minimized by the system so it's going to
take
on average the system is going to do
what it expects to do which in this case
is
get to some region in the state space
that it prefers to inhabit
um what makes that not a tautology and
what makes it something that we can
actually operationalize and ask
interesting questions about is the fact
that there is this nice connection to
inference there are all of these
explicit mathematical tools that we can
use to talk about surprising
minimization not just as the kind of
information theoretic statement of
systems that aren't surprising
or systems that aren't surprised
due on surprising things it ends up a
little bit more nuanced than that and so
so to me the free energy principle is
this whole host of results uh about
um
random dynamical systems and especially
random dynamical systems which are
organized or which self-organize
think that is uh
how i would think of it and it's and
it's got some physics and
uh stuff that that we can actually talk
about in that context
awesome thanks both for those great
answers i'm pulling up the paper
and
so many things in what you said i just
wanted to follow up on but let's follow
the main line of the paper and wherever
you think there's some dots that could
be connected or any questions arising or
areas of future research or the
connection to applications that you're
working on or other people might think
about getting involved in we can just
take those little cul-de-sacs from the
main line
so i have the paper up
on bayesian mechanics of physics of and
by beliefs the two of you are the first
authors there's also connor heinz magnus
kudo barron millage lancelot decosta
brandon klein and carl fristen
any just overview notes on again like
what led to this team or anything like
that
while we're on this first page
um well
from my perspective uh you know daldon
and i have been talking a lot about this
kind of stuff for the last year
year and a half two years
um
and uh
yeah
i i won't i won't try to
i'll try not to be too uh
overly generous dalton but like i think
uh
yeah uh
so
some of dalton's work um has i think
changed the way that we uh think about
uh the fep uh
in particular um
what what dalton did in this great paper
towards a geometry and analysis
for
bayesian mechanics is to show that the
free energy principle and the principle
of constrained axon entropy are actually
dual to each other they are two sides of
the same coin
and i i you know i've been um
i've been following this line of uh work
for uh quite some time and i think it it
foundationally changes the way that we
think about the fep it moves it from
like this um some might say exotic
result from you know theoretical uh
neurobiology to uh
you know it connects it back up to
um the foundations of contemporary
physics effectively by showing that you
know
this thing that we we understand and
almost take for granted uh you know
maximum entropy inference procedures
turn out to connect up to
uh this free energy literature in a
non-trivial way so i think the paper
started out
and it didn't end this way but i think
we started off trying to write a
reader-friendly companion
to uh the work that dalton had done um
but by the end of it realized that this
was more um
i think the dalton's paper towards
geometry and analysis for uh bayesian
mechanics pillars
i think it stands uh on its own as a
piece of mathematical reasoning so it is
an exercise in a maximum of entropy
inference math and it shows that you can
recover uh some of the really core
results of the free energy formulation
just using the language of constraint
maximum entropy in particular dalton
approves the approximate bayesian
inference lemma that had uh you know
caused so much discussion in our
literature
for the last bit
and so you know uh i think the the paper
grew out of that um
and
yeah the
the team is something of a who's who of
like the
you know the the core contributors to
this literature and just from a
strategic point of view it was important
for us to have like you know lance
decosta
carl fristen you know connor hines and
folks that had been
i think contributing to this core
formulation and in particular to the
development of uh
you know this new framing of the free
energy stuff a bayesian mechanics
um
so yeah i think that the paper grew out
of that and if dalton's paper is this
kind of dalton's stent like the towards
the geometry and analysis for bayesian
mechanics is a kind of standalone piece
of mathematical reasoning this is more
about how this actually fits into the
free energy principle literature so this
is very much more a free energy
principle literature paper
um
and yeah we were hoping to do you know
as reader friendly an introduction as we
could uh there are actually two
whole kind of introductory sections in
the paper um but we ended up doing a lot
of i think important work uh in that
paper connecting up to the free energy
principle
i hope that helps answer me
great answer and welcome lars would you
like to give any overviews or notes
before we jump into the sections of the
paper
hey thanks thanks for
sending me the link there maxwell allow
me on here um no nothing really to add
there i'm just here as a spectator i
have a few questions as we go down along
and maybe i can throw into the
conversation but um yeah thanks for
having me on
awesome
all right
so the abstract begins with a really
clear aim the aim of this paper is to
introduce a field of study that has
emerged over the last decade called
bayesian mechanics and we're going to be
unpacking that claim so suffice to say
the abstract very clear and summarizes
some of the core points that we're going
to delve into now
we're looking now at the contents
so
what led to the sections the paper being
this way
and in this order
what did you feel like it was important
to include what did you feel like it was
important to introduce and why
well so
if you look i'll i'll actually pull it
up in front of me so that we uh we're
all talking about the same thing
um
give me one second
and it's viewable in in large size on
the live stream so yeah feel free to
have your own copy up but i'll have
whatever section we're looking at will
be very visible on the live stream
well uh maxwell is grabbing his copy um
i'll just give a couple of contextual
remarks
so like maxwell described i mean
originally
i had released this set of results about
what we call approximate bayesian
inference
and
the sort of mathematical basis for some
of the key ideas
in the fep literature
up until that point anyway
um
and originally it was
meant to
be a much shorter paper that just
dissected some of those results and
related them back to the fep in a way
that was a little more concrete and a
way that people who actually work on the
ftp might might care a little more about
um because of course the stuff that i
wrote about is
um a little far removed from the fep
even though it's an object of
inspiration for the results in the in
that paper um
there is a reading of that paper where
it's
formally pretty distinct from the fep
so so originally that was the goal is
just give it some extra
physics intuition and some extra
connection to the actual fep
it became something a little bit
different as we were building this out
and we realized okay there are a whole
instead of of new results um not only
mine but also from uh
carl's tnb group and from others folks
and and they all really should be
tied together nicely and part of that is
the you know connecting the geometry and
analysis paper to the actual fep part of
it is actually talking about
what we would think of the fep as today
um
that shaped the table of contents a
little bit because a lot of what we then
wanted to go and say is okay we have
this
theory
of the free energy principle
one of the key ideas
in the way that we're viewing the free
energy principle today
is that it is just a bit of physics it
is it is much like classical mechanics
or statistical mechanics
um it has a set of mathematical uh
results that sort of hang around it that
give it a nice foundation and it applies
to specific systems and describes them
in a specific way
and and that was why we began with both
an overview of
what is mechanics what do we talk about
in physics when we say mechanics and
also section three is what is the free
energy principle what what have we
talked about so far in the literature
and and what might we define as bayesian
mechanics so what is what is the physics
of beliefs or systems that carry beliefs
so that that's sort of
excuse me that's sort of um shaped the
the first uh maybe 20 pages of the
papers it's just building out the theory
and the context for the theory
afterwards is is a bit of a uh
sort of change in um
our uh
line of attack but
but you'll see it does remain very
similar so so i won't uh get too far
ahead of myself
great
any other notes maxwell or we can carry
on
i think that that's a
that's a great summary i think uh
yeah we
we try to keep this as self-contained as
possible as a paper so you know the the
two
uh
you know introductory sections
uh are meant to
uh provide some kind of visual uh
intuition for a lot of the more formal
results that are discussed in the paper
and in you know the the papers that it
builds on um we have uh you know the
artistic brilliance of brennan klein uh
that's added uh to this paper so uh you
know i think the the illustrations help
um the idea was that you know
based on dalton's work we we are
formulating basically a geometry and
analysis
for the core results and the free energy
principle literature so we thought
let's leverage
uh
the geometric nature of a lot of these
intuitions to really illustrate them
and so
yeah
that i think explains a lot of the
structure and the paper ends on
some philosophical considerations
and hopefully clarifies some of the
confusions or misunderstandings
uh understandable misunderstandings uh
that have arisen um
yeah so i think that no that does really
address uh i guess the last thing to
point out is uh we we introduced this
uh field of study
uh in the
last section that we uh we call g theory
um which is i think the direction that
we're going to be moving in for a while
which uh
is um yeah formulating uh
the free energy principle in the
bayesian mechanics in terms of maximum
caliber so
extending this duality
between
the
density dynamics formulation of the free
energy principle in terms of that
probability densities over states
and maximum constrained maximum entropy
to path-based uh formulations so
path entropy is called caliber and you
can
dalton is one of the few world
specialists in maximum caliber
uh
and yeah maximum caliber is a maximum
path entropy so it's the same idea as
maximum entropy but
you're considering the entropy of paths
and
we have had you know the free energy
principle started
off as a formulated in terms of paths
after all it is a version of the you
know the principle of stationary action
it leads us to write down paths of
stationary action and so the uh
the ambition now is to connect these
things up much more formally so that uh
we can uh
we can handle
really genuine non-equilibria
uh things like wandering uh markov
blankets and uh yeah moving attractors
and all that kind of stuff which find uh
you know a home much more naturally in
the language of maximum caliber did you
did you want to add anything to that
belton you're really the uh max cal
expert
um no i think that's uh that's a good
account of um one of the key future
directions is you know we spend the
first half introducing bayesian
mechanics
we spend the second half talking about
where bayesian mechanics fits into the
rest of statistical mechanics and uh
high energy physics by connecting it to
max end and
to gauge theory
and this is where some of the geometric
stuff comes in
and then the the very last thing we do
we sort of cap it off by saying okay now
you know
we've talked a lot about bayesian
mechanics we've talked a lot about
maximum entropy bayesian mechanics
but there is in some sense much more
natural formulation of bayesian
mechanics in terms of dynamics because
ultimately that's what we're thinking
about is dynamical systems and the way
that they evolve in time the way that
they flow over their state space
and there's there's a sense in which
not only is it much more natural
mathematically it just works easier it
looks prettier it's so it's much nicer
there's also a sense in which it's it's
meaningless to talk about states of a
process which is constantly in flux
so
limiting ourselves to densities over
states
as exists in the last
you know couple of years of the
literature
um which has in fact not always been the
case some of the early stuff
is written in terms of generalized
coordinates of motion which are nothing
but a particular way of talking about
dynamics and therefore paths
um
so
there's a sense in which the the recent
um detour into
states is very limiting not only
mathematically but conceptually limiting
and we can see that directly in the way
that it is um
handling things like non-markovian
processes uh or processes that change
with statistics that are out of
equilibrium
so so at the very end we say you know
we've done all this work
um the the
best next step is to take all of this
and and all this stuff that we've just
done about maximum entropy basic
mechanics and put it in dynamical terms
and this necessitates passing to what we
call maximum caliber which is uh also
due to jains originally it's the
principle of path entropy
um
but uh
eventually you know the goal is we would
be able to write all of this stuff uh
and in particular we'd have to be able
to generalize what we have written
into a language that's much more
dynamical and and uh
and max cal we already know uh has
demonstrated uh an immense uh success in
treating non-equilibrium processes so
mathematically i mean there's reason to
be very optimistic about what we will
gain
when we generalize the duality that
we've talked about previously uh and so
it really does seem like it's it's the
ideal thing to do in the very near
future
awesome
let's jump into the sections
so section one is the introduction
and just one part that uh
i wanted to highlight the footnotes are
so informative there's some of these
motifs like we set out to make it as
simple as possible and four pages was
our limit but then we ended up
innovating this way so that's one funny
motif and then the other funny motif
that i see
is um the super informative footnote
often because maybe it's possible to
just make the claim stand alone and
indirect response to somewhere else so
that's very exciting and interesting
like
footnote 1
covers a lot of the prerequisite
fields
like dynamical systems theory calculus
probability and information theory so i
found that to be very interesting
because it helps understand where we can
come from and what kinds of backgrounds
we'd want to be learning about and then
also a very important
distinction
of the two meanings of the word belief
in the probabilistic sense of bayesian
statistics or the propositional or folk
understanding as you write from
philosophy and cognitive science so um
just thought those were two interesting
footnotes and and reflected like part of
the process and the discourse around the
primary text and how that can be
clarified in this format
feel free to make any overall comments
on that or that's just getting to page
three
um
well about the um the prerequisites
it's a it's a difficult um
it's a difficult balance to achieve in
some sense right because
um we don't want to be academic
gatekeepers no one benefits from
gatekeeping but these are also highly
technical fields
um so you know
i've been joking for you know the last
few months if you've never taken a
derivative you're gonna have a bad time
in this literature it's just not the
kind of thing that lends itself to um
you know
surface engagement in some sense like
it's very and especially with these um
these new developments i mean uh there's
dalton's work uh that basically shows
that the free energy principle is dual
to uh maximum entropy maximum caliber so
there's this kind of deep connection to
i mean effectively
the the core of contemporary
physics uh and there's the there are
these new results uh that show that the
free energy principle is asymptotically
equivalent to the principle of unitarity
from quantum mechanics
uh you know there's there are these new
quantum formulations of fep that have uh
popped up
so
yeah i mean
navigating the space comfortably
presupposes a lot
and the good news is that it's hard for
everyone so
there's uh
there's something to learn for everyone
uh you know i spent the last uh three
years of my life teaching myself like
category theory and gage theory and
stuff which turned out to be very useful
uh you know connecting up with dalton
and
make doing all of this work but now uh
we're launching ourselves into quantum
theory which i'm less familiar with so
there's something to find difficult for
everyone
but um yeah
it i i really do think that to fully
appreciate
going on here
um
some technical prerequisites are
important um otherwise we're led to
making uh false assertions like i see
this circulate a lot that
dynamical systems approaches uh are
contradictory to uh information
theoretic approaches which is just
nonsense from a formal point of view um
yeah information metrics naturally
re-emerge when you're considering for
example uh
how do you measure distances in
state space effectively it's just yeah
so
the the more uh mathematical background
one comes with i think the easier it is
to integrate
into this um
yeah
yes well indeed there's a lot of
encouraging and good news and hopefully
a community that also values
participation and accessibility as well
so
agreed important general points there
um yeah before we move on i'll say
something really quickly about this
second book
just because it's it's a remark that's
actually pretty important to me in fact
maxwell's the one who wrote it but uh
i i didn't even realize but it is an
important um clarification that when we
talk about beliefs and an inference
it's it's much more general than just
uh an agent
or a cognitive
object
um
the the manner in which we talk about
inference and we talk about carrying
beliefs is this this much more general
sense of just
two random dynamical systems that
are coupled and and therefore
reflect the statistics of each other so
it could be
a i mean generically this is a system
estimating the statistics of an
embedding environment
the very important point is any system
with any noise and in fact systems with
no noise have statistics and so any
system that estimates or couples to
another system with statistics
can be interpreted as mathematical
inference that one system performs
inference about the other
the the sort of content that you place
on that idea of inference is very case
dependent so it's not the case that that
stones for instance are cognitive but it
is very much the case that stones
reflect the statistics of their
environment simply because these two
systems are coupled and their statistics
reflect each other and so this is what
we mean in the sense of talking about
agents that carry beliefs simply it is
about objects that do this kind of
statistical estimation which we think of
as inference but it's it's certainly
much more general than simply something
like a reinforcement learning agent that
actually stores representation of its
environment um it is a representation
but in a much more trivial sense in the
general case
i mean i would i would add to that by
pointing out that um you know dalton was
saying that we
there were there were disadvantages to
focusing on the density dynamics
formulation which features markov
blankets and the like up so marco
blankets are great and we like them um
but i think uh focusing on them so much
in the literature over the last several
years has obscured the fact that uh the
the free energy principle is at core
a statement about how you know as dalton
was uh saying earlier random dynamical
systems couple to each other so you know
the markov blanket is not some i often
hear and read in the literature um the
markov blanket secludes the organism
from its environment but it's not that's
not that's not the idea at all
uh the markov blanket is the set of
states by which the organism and its
environment are coupled and in fact the
you know we made this case in a neat
paper on a variational approach to niche
construction several years ago
you can basically swap the sensory and
active states uh
of your organism and you get sensory and
active states of an environment it is
fundamentally a story about how uh
systems couple uh and synchronize with
each other uh it's not a story about how
uh
yeah
things that exist or somehow secluded
from an environment it's it's really a
story about how yeah we uh
we
we become a model of our environment
meaning that we are like in tune with
engaged with and reflecting the
structure of that environment this
becomes very clear by the way when you
look at the quantum formulations of the
free energy principle
if you take the asymptotic limit of the
free energy principle so its behavior is
time tends towards infinity um for
classical systems that have space time
individuation what you get is something
like the good regulator theorem so
i become as much as possible as i can
like my environment uh you know modulo
this space time separation i can't be my
environment because i'm here and it's
there in some sense and then what you
get in that context is statistical
mirroring but in in the quantum context
when there is no space like separation
between systems the fep tends uh
towards um entanglement
so systems that uh are related in an fep
theoretic way at the quantum level uh
become entangled that is precisely what
the fep does
conforming to the fep means that systems
become maximally entangled
so it really is not a statement about
you know
how organisms are separate from their
environment
it's a statement about how organisms are
or
things in general self-organizing
systems individuate and couple
simultaneously to
their environments and how that's not a
contradiction
excellent um so as we
rush through section one and head to
section two i just wanted to pull out
two really key quotes you wrote in this
paper we discussed the relationship
between dynamics mechanics and
principles
and then
later on page five you write bayesian
mechanics is specialized for particular
systems that have a partition of states
and go on to describe it more so as we
head towards section 2
an overview of the idea of mechanics and
indeed bayesian mechanics could you
unpack a little bit by what you mean
dynamics mechanics and principles
sure um so mel andrews uh as everyone i
think in the literature knows now wrote
this great paper uh the math is not the
territory um which challenged us to be
very clear about what we meant really uh
when we're talking about the free energy
principle and active inference and in
there
i think mel makes a number of
contributions but one of their most
important contributions is to
differentiate between
the fep as an uninterpreted uh formal
structure
and the fep
as it might figure in applications to
model specific kinds of systems
and uh mel points out that you know
the a lot of the confusion in the
philosophical literature has to do with
the fact that the the primary ftp
literature often doesn't differentiate
between
the just the mathematical structure of
the theory and then these models
interpreted as representing certain
features of
a target system that we want to make
sense of
and that's important because
falsification
uh or verification empirical validation
more generally um applies to one kind of
thing but not the other right so uh the
the free energy principle in so far it
is as it is a mathematical theory i.e
like a formal statement
is no more falsifiable or subject to
empirical verification than calculus
would be
right like you wouldn't you wouldn't try
to falsify the axioms of calculus they
do or do not apply informatively to
certain kinds of systems so there's a
level at which the core formal results
of the fpp are have that status
their mathematical results
and
we can use this to
uh you know do some interesting
empirical stuff
so uh what we wanted to do is to
differentiate between three kinds of uh
formal things in the first class of
tools that
mel was outlining
namely we distinguish between dynamics
mechanics and principles
so the dynamics are descriptive they are
basically a
formal description of some systems
behavior
you might say that like galilean
mechanics is
almost entirely
dynamics
you know the
you needed someone like newton
to come around and say well there are uh
general equations of motion that one can
write down to account for
uh
sort of how these
how this description
plays out in some sense uh so we move
from dynamics
to mechanics
uh in the same way that we move from
description to explanation from a target
phenomenon that is formalized in a
certain way that we would like to have
an explanation for to a set of equations
of motion that really account for
how those dynamics come to be
and then principles
if if mechanics tell you how
principles tell you why
so usually
in physics we appeal to
some symmetry or conservation principle
in order to derive the mechanics or the
mechanical theory for the the systems in
question
so what we're left with is principles
mechanics and dynamics all of which are
formal theories and once you have a
mechanics you can apply it to study
specific kinds of systems empirically
and that's where empirical verification
would come in so principles are not
falsifiable they're just bits of math
and you use them to write down
mechanical theories which when
interpreted in the right context and
when the variables are mapped onto
things that are of interest target
systems then they become subject to
empirical evaluation
so hopefully that um
you know uh
clarifies a lot of the model around uh
around the fep one of the reasons why we
spent so long you know outlining the
idea of mechanics and physics is that
this isn't some exotic
way of thinking about things this is
really just physics
just
straight
vanilla
reasoning from physics um
yeah i'll stop there dalton has probably
some interesting things to add
no i think
i think you've covered it um
yeah it's it's just that there are
important formal differences in physics
between what we would call a mechanical
theory for
some object and a dynamical description
of some object
and so in this tower of
things
you get
ideas you get theories that sit at
different layers in the tower
this hierarchy ends up being useful in
clarifying uh
this host of different results in the
fep and where one fits into the other so
it was important to take the time to
discuss it
but
that was that and that's the whole point
of section two
awesome so to also move quickly through
section two on page nine
you write we are concerned here with
what we have called bayesian mechanics
and then you launch into
an example of mechanical theory
operationalizing a mathematical
principle
and you provide some
classical statistical formulations on
page 10.
so could you give us an overview of what
the equations on page 10 are showing
like what they do for classical physics
and what is the analogy or what is the
connection that this is preparing us to
make with bayesian mechanics
yes uh well in fact i have an entire
paper uh
that's about to come out about this just
like building on the analogy um so i'll
uh
leave that as an easter egg for the
audience watch out for a classical
physics for the bayesian mechanic paper
because i think instant classic
it might be some interest yeah
might be of some interest but yeah so on
page 10 um
we are just giving an example of
the of this kind of formal difference so
you have um some kind of principle
in classical physics it is the principle
that systems um
are kind of lazy you know they
there is some kind of uh
an amount of energy that it takes to get
from a to b
and systems don't waste that energy uh
so they take precisely the shortest path
from a to b or the path of least energy
in in the more technical sense of the
transfer
of potential energy into kinetic energy
so if you have some amount of stored
energy the transfer of that into energy
of motion is minimized along the path
that's a very um
[Music]
abstract statement and there's not a lot
that you can actually do with that
computationally all you can say is you
know the systems
systems uh try and get from a to b
using the shortest amount of motion
possible no extra motion so so if you
see in figure one for instance uh there
are these paths that fly off into
sort of these these very strange
fluctuations in the classical world
those fluctuations don't exist because
classical systems take this uh energy
minimizing uh parabolic path in the
darker blue
what is computational about that is that
principle of stationary action so the
principle that you don't waste energy
um results in
a
mechanical theory a law of motion
for the mechanics of classical objects
this is what we would call newton's law
newton's second law in particular it's
this
everyone knows f equals m a it's uh
force equals mass times acceleration
so the idea is that
if you are such a system if you
minimize the amount of energy that you
take
then
the acceleration of you must obey
precisely the force being applied to you
uh and um and so this is your your law
of motion this is a mechanical theory
the dynamics that come out of that
are able to be discussed when you start
putting in actual details when you plug
in whatever force being applied
uh sorry that's a dog you probably heard
it
uh what is what is the force being
applied to the system what are the
initial conditions for the system what
is the mass for the system all this
extra data starts giving you
trajectories so an actual model of the
system which is less explanatory and
more descriptive and this is at the very
bottom of the hierarchy where you get
this dynamical theory that's got all
this extra data in it
so this is this is very quickly an
account of the
that hierarchy
awesome
let's move into section three and figure
two
so the caption is three faces of
bayesian mechanics
what are the three faces of bayesian
mechanics and what is this figure
showing
well
it's
it's often been
suggested that there are like 17 000
versions of the free energy principle
and that it's not very clear you know
what the current version is and all that
stuff and some of this is fair
and some of it isn't i think some of it
is fair because it is true that
often in the technical papers
not sufficient care has been given to
you know ex making very explicit which
assumptions we're making about the
systems that we're interested in
modeling
um so what we tried to do in section
three is to provide a comprehensive
survey of all of the ways that the free
energy principle has been articulated
in the literature
um and so it turns out that there are
basically three main ways in which the
fep has been applied which we're
representing here
so we've already alluded to the first
distinction um the fep can either be
formulated in terms of a probability
density over states directly
or
as a probability density over paths
so over trajectories of states that we
write in so-called generalized
coordinates um
and those are importantly different um
so the the literature
over the last i guess like circa 2009
2012 to 2019
focused
you know
almost exclusively on the uh density
over states formulation and this is
where you get um
you know the approximate bayesian
inference lemma that's played uh a
pretty critical role in a lot of these
investigations this is also where you
get
uh
like states that play the role of markov
blankets effectively
um
whereas the original formulation of the
fep was in terms of a probability
density over paths so you're not you're
not really
so much interested in in the you know
the the the dynamics of a system just in
terms of how probable states are what
you're actually interested in
is you know entire trajectories uh that
unfold over time
and um the the most general you know
paths formulation doesn't make a lot of
the um assumptions that have been
criticized over the last little
bit so
importantly uh we don't assume that the
systems being described are stationary
um we don't assume that uh
you know and accordingly we don't assume
that the system has a non-equilibrium a
steady state
and we're now returning to this
formulation because it's less
restrictive uh
you know for reasons that uh the dolphin
could probably detail uh better than i
can um so
then within the density over states
formulation
um what you get is this kind of mode
tracking or mode matching behavior
where um i mean essentially what we're
saying is that
a
system that conforms to the free energy
principle is such that it looks as if
the average internal state is tracking
the average external state or
like
matching it and the the relevant
difference
in that
density over states formulation is that
the
external mode that the system is
tracking can have dynamics to it or can
also not
um and it was important to distinguish
these cases because a lot of the formal
analysis so for example our colleagues
at sussex
released this great paper how particular
are the physics of the free energy
principle
and they come to the conclusion that uh
there's
the fep doesn't really have anything
interesting to say about the class of
systems that they examined
what is the class of systems that they
examined
they are looking at linear systems uh
that undergo
dissipation effectively so uh
physically these are dampened springs
right so uh to restate if you take away
the mathematical uh baggage what they're
saying is the fep doesn't have anything
particularly interesting to say about uh
the behavior of dampened springs so what
does a dampened spring do well it starts
off
and then it dissipates back to
a fixed point if you're burning
right like
just due to friction um so
the mode
towards which the system is flowing has
no dynamics to it it is a fixed point it
just dissipates back to a fixed point
and what they're showing is that
there's nothing interesting to say
from an fep theoretic perspective about
those systems but
i mean the the counterpoint is sort of
that there isn't interesting anything
interesting
theoretically to say about those systems
there isn't any interesting uh external
dynamics that uh the internal dynamics
would be matching
and a lot of these null results uh where
we
we use fvp technology to say stuff about
a system and there's nothing interesting
to say look at systems that have fixed
modes
fixed external modes and so you know
the the the idea is that you know the
fep applies vacuously
to those systems because there's nothing
interesting to say
um so
yeah
to
to summarize my rant
um
we uh we tried to
summarize the main applications of the
fep in the literature we identified
three
um and strategically uh we point out
where some commentators may have been
led astray
uh by focusing on one rather than the
other so in particular a lot of this
these ideas that the fep can't handle
things like you know systems with moving
attractors and uh you know systems that
don't have like a single mode um
that this these are understandable
characterizations given that basically
since 2000 from 2018 to 2 sorry 2012 to
mostly focused on this middle class of
systems so systems that uh we're
describing in terms of the density over
states uh that have a dynamic mode so
it's understandable why people would
focus their attention on that um but the
fep in its most general form doesn't
make
you know perhaps problematic assumptions
like stationarity um and it yeah it it
also applies interestingly to systems
that have interesting external state
dynamics um so strategically i think
that's what we were going for in this
section
um and i i believe this is the only
place in the entire literature where
this is reviewed so comprehensively in
terms of this tripartite distinction um
so you know i i don't mean to be
disingenuous and to suggest that you
know
the confusions that have arisen are only
due to um
you know just
a lack of paying attention these things
have not been expressed very clearly the
assumptions have not always been stated
very clearly and
yeah
the the form of uh the path of least
action in each of these things looks
very different um so it we can also
understand why it might seem like there
are 17 versions of the free energy
principle
um but there aren't
thank you maxwell
as we speed through this section i'll
just note that formalism 1 on page 15 is
familiar and has to do with the flow of
states in the particular partition
and we've also seen the helmholtz
decomposition shown in figure 3 in terms
of a decomposition on
into the vertical and the horizontal the
gradient pursuing and the solenoidal
isocontour aspect of flow those are
reviewed in the citations that are
provided here so let's get into the
newer stuff
um
in section four you're discussing some
mathematic mathematical preliminaries on
the maximum entropy principle gage
theory and dualization but first yes
lars
moving on to section 4
section 3 was
incredibly illuminating for me
personally and i think the literature in
general and having the separation out
and there was a question that arose for
me and working through this that
i just wanted to throw out there
um i don't want to distract the journey
through the paper too much but
in
moving to this um you talk about on page
um when the ftp is applied to density
over states as opposed to path we assume
a non-equilibrium steady state density
and then on the next page
page 20 you see we can view this
this non-equilibrium study state density
is providing a set of prior preference
preferences which lead the particular
system
um
to look like it attempts to enact and
bring about
these preferences through action if you
then move to the path-based formulation
where there is no nest assumption
how do you recover
these preferences
in
in that formulation
or can you not use that formulation to
describe systems that are doing actions
that look like they have preferences or
is there a piece that i'm missing does
that make sense
um i can take that one so um one of the
one of the key uh deliverables of this
third section is
this three phases type thing right so
the idea of the free energy principle
and
and the mechanical theory that arises
from it
is we would want a
mechanical theory a law of motion for
bayesian inference or for systems that
do basic inference and what it ends up
being is approximate bayesian inference
and and this comes in three flavors mode
matching
mode tracking or path track this is the
the three faces thing
so that i mean just like you have
different flavors of classroom mechanics
you have things that move continuously
like satellites in orbit or you have
things that
move and then stop moving like a bull
thrown through the air eventually
returns to the ground and things that
sit on the ground don't move unless
they're acted upon so there are very
different flavors of approximate basin
infants and these three are in
particular the kinds of things that
we're thinking about so
the reason why i give that context is
because we can still imagine preferences
on the paths of a system
a system must evolve in such a way that
it avoids certain areas of the state
space
given that it remains a system so uh you
know
uh a human can't
evolve in such a way that it dips too
far away from its allostatic
bounds there are certain set points and
certain bounds around those set points
in which i can oscillate but too far
outside of those bounds and
i'm in trouble
likewise you know i can have something
like a stone that kind of
evolves through a state space the stone
doesn't have preferences per se but it
has
a definition
and and so we can read not um
preferences but definitions about what a
stone looks like in the same sense as we
understand what a human looks like as
certain preferences that guarantee
cohesion so things that are definitional
of a stone
um guarantee that same kind of cohesion
that just
there's a type error if you would
identify them but but you know
mathematically they end up looking very
similar
and and what's interesting about that is
now you can talk about preferences or
you can talk about definitions along the
path of evolution of a system a stone
must stay
roughly together it must stay in this
sort of crystalline structure
if you start uh
hammering away at it you turn it into a
powder this is something that we
wouldn't think of as a stone
so so in the same sense if a human
um
doesn't eat
for too long
and and maybe starves to death it's a
really grim example but unfortunately um
it's one of the better ones you can
imagine you know you're you're drifting
too far away from this um
this state of being satiated or having
sufficient energy to
maintain um
cellular uh
processes and the chemical reactions
that sustain life and as a result you
know
the the preference along your set of
paths uh has been violated um so i think
yes there is a sense in which even
though we have forgone a nest density
per se we still have a density over over
paths not over states that this density
still expresses something of a
definition for the system or a set of
preferences for the system without which
we don't have a conceptualization of
that system
that's that's a very long answer to your
question but but maybe it satisfies you
no that's that's great thank you so much
it was really useful that makes sense
you you can kind of think about it as
these constraints force systems to
basically pick trajectories that are at
the trial
of uh you know a preference landscape or
a constraint landscape if you want to
think about it so you get the same kind
of thing as dalton was saying but it's
not the systems aren't assumed to be
stationary so they're not um you know
non-equilibrium steady-state
distributions per se
but there is something analogous
uh and a lot of the uh
future work in g theory is precisely
about using the technology of maximum
caliber to really make sense of this
formally
um let's move into section four
so in section four as noted and as
referenced to the previous publication
there's a discussion that the fep is
dueled to the constrained maximum
entropy principle
and then one of the ways that that's
pursued in this section is through the
lens or at least related to gauge theory
so
we're looking at figure four
what is gauge theory what does category
theory duel and how is it being deployed
in this situation
um i guess i'll take that one as well uh
figure four you said
yes
okay
illustration of fiber bundles sections
the big mega figures
oh yeah okay yeah uh well mega fig i i
recognize that name i i believe that's
how we refer to it internally
uh yeah well
so
if you ask me
um because i am a mathematician
primarily
uh
if you were to ask me or if you were to
ask a mathematician what is a gauge
theory
you would probably get a response
roughly like well gage theory is the
study of
a particular geometric space called a
fiber bundle
so there is there is a type of space
called the fiber bundle in geometry uh
it looks exactly like that figure it's a
bunch of fibers pasted onto
um something on the bottom uh what we
call a base manifold
and uh and studying how do things behave
in
a space like this how do they behave in
the sort of fibers and how does that
reflect some kind of behavior on the
base manifold
these are interesting geometric
questions
that arise in the study of fiber bundles
and hence in what is called gage theory
if you're a physicist i mean it turns
out that
fiber bundles are the natural
space for talking about um classical uh
gauge theories so the theory of certain
high-energy particles
um but it's but it's a little bit more
general than that
uh and so if you're a physicist this is
what you think if you think about um
like
gauge bosons uh but but this is only
because fiber bundles are very natural
way of talking about these things and so
it is a little bit more general
what we're talking about in the figure
four is this idea that uh
in this space of fibers
uh you can
kind of trace out um surfaces and that
these surfaces are like probability
densities over the base manifold and in
fact they aren't just like probability
densities they are so you can formulate
probabilities over a state space as an
object in a fiber bundle
and therefore
if you have all the technology available
to you you can draw this very nice gauge
theoretic interpretation
of what it means to be
a probability density
and therefore because the object of
basic mechanics is systems that do
inference and so systems that estimate
probability densities there is a nice
gauge theoretic interpretation to
bayesian mechanics that hinges pretty
much on this picture
what we would call the the gauge in this
situation
is the uh choice of this j function so
you see you have several different
surfaces uh three of them each of which
comes with a different choice of j
uh so the the idea of choosing a
function in the fibers
and therefore choosing a
shape for your surface
this is what we would think of as a
gauge theory and and that's why
i went down this route in the geometry
and analysis paper because it ends up
drawing a very nice picture of what it
might mean to
engage in
constrained inference
awesome and could i give a pedestrian or
so the the bystander
yeah the the more the less technical
version of it is uh so gage theories and
dalton correct me whenever i say
something that's wildly or even not so
wildly inaccurate but gage theories are
basically how one would
how one articulates
symmetries or conservation laws and
contemporary physics
so most physics relies on the idea that
um
some transformations that are of
interest like the ones uh described by
maxwell's equations uh
have some kind of symmetry or or that
concern i think a slightly better way of
going about it would be to say that you
know modern physics is broken up roughly
into
stuff
and forces
yeah and forces act on stuff
and stuff gets acted on by forces
so the interesting thing in gage theory
is you can talk about how a definition
of some stuff
the shape of some stuff
is intimately dependent on the forces
acting on the stuff
and so this is where we get this idea of
we have a a particular
shape to our surface we have some you
know probabilities over our states but
that this is actually defined by
the the the choice of gauge this this j
function so
our assignment of probability two states
is actually determined not by
probability but it's determined by the
constraints on those states certain
states are preferable certain states are
not
unpreferable states get low probability
preferable states get high probability
and our notion of preferability is
encoded in the choice of j it's a
function that constrains
different states so constraints in this
case are like penalties uh so our
assignment of penalties so our choice of
force is actually what shapes our
assignment of probability that's
ultimately um
i think uh well that's a slightly
different way of viewing um the geometry
of the situation is gage theory is all
about these kinds of what we would call
covariance relationships covariance
meaning literally two things varying
together if i choose a force i'm i'm
forced to choose
some stuff
uh and likewise if i choose some stuff
that necessitates uh an underlying
choice of force
so gauge covariance ends up being very
helpful
in situations like this
thanks
let's see if we can touch on some of
these last figures
in figure 5
we see a vector field on a curve that's
reminding us of that sort of baseball
diamond shape from earlier with the path
of least action
and in figure 6 a probability density is
generated by level sets of the
constraint function
j so either figure five or figure six
whichever you feel fits in best here
what is being shown and where were you
going with it how is it connected to
alternative phrasings
yeah i guess i'll just cut to figure six
which is kind of about this covariance
thing so if i choose
a
particular functional form for j in this
case it's a penalty that is proportional
to distance
i would expect my assignment of
probability to fall off
roughly like a distance function so it
should it should be probability of a
state should decrease as the penalty on
a state increases so in this case the
probability of a state should decrease
as i go away from some central point and
it should do so symmetrically and and so
we would expect a gaussian density from
this
and it is indeed the case that uh you
can understand
the covariance as a kind of projecting
down and then lifting back up
and what do you get when you do that
well the stuff in the equation the
probability uh ends up being defined by
where you take all of the sort of rings
on the the j function you project them
down
you get circles on the base manifold
when you lift them back up they're rings
and so we know a symmetric
probability density with a whole bunch
of rings is just a gaussian probability
density
so so this this figure is kind of
capturing um what does this covariance
relationship actually look like how do
we actually build stuff out of forces
and and it ends up being the case that
it's this very simple recipe of you push
everything down
and then you lift it back up
and the lift is e to the j
so the so you place j on to x
uh that's the first step your second
step is then you hit it with this
exponential function and e to the minus
x squared is of course a gaussian
density so that's all that figure 6 is
depicting it's just zooming in on one of
the objects in figure
4.
great and i thought um on page 34 also
the striking result that the splitting
of the flow of a system into vertical
and horizontal components under the
constrained maximum entropy principle is
isomorphic to the helmholtz
decomposition of the flow of the
autonomous partition of a particular
system so for those who are caught up
with the way that the helmholtz
decomposition was used for example in
the papers that we discussed in live
stream 32 with markov blankets and chaos
stochastic chaos this is augmenting it
or transposing it into
another formalization
um and
moving on again quickly um it's worth
pointing out that there is uh
there are some significant advantages to
reformulating things in in terms of
maximum entropy um
uh i'll
i'll let you know delta and speak to the
more technical uh
parts of this but i guess
one um
one thing that pops out to me more
politically is that uh maximum entropy
and constrained maximum entropy
i mean they are just core parts of the
physicist toolbox
so
the fact that we are able to
reproduce the helmholtz decomposition in
terms of the way that flow splits up in
the gauge theoretic formulation i think
is quite significant
it gives us an entirely independent line
of reasoning arising at the same results
so uh you know especially due to
some
some work by martin beale and colleagues
a few years ago we were not we were no
longer sure whether some of these
results uh
obtained you know the
there had been doubt thrown on to the
derivations of the approximate bayesian
inference lemma in some papers uh
life as we know it from 2013 i believe
is the paper that they targeted uh one
way of reading this is that independent
of all these analyses and independent of
whether bl and colleagues are correct
about their criticism of the 2013 paper
this is an independent derivation that
just follows from
uncontroversial mathematics and we're
able to re-uh re-derive basically the
the main core uh portions of the formal
results uh that carl had derived so the
approximate bayesian inference lemma the
helmholtz decomposition um and i mean
in some sense
the the magic is that we understand now
why these arise to begin with
uh there's uh
yeah
i think they're
the um
the maximum entropy interpretation um in
some sense especially in the the gauge
theoretic formulation in some sense
tells us well
why why does approximate bayesian
entrance work
just full stop and these sets of results
explain you know effectively why this
has to be the case
only my facilitator hat prevents me from
being that excited
um
section 5.4 also explored more in the
previous citation so the four things
that i wanted to just touch on as
briefly as people wanted as we close are
the three philosophical areas that are
introduced in section six and then of
course just the appetizer of g theory so
in page 38
section 6 the philosophy of bayesian
mechanics
6.1 addresses clarifying the epistemic
status of the fep so
what were you aiming to
bring people's attention to and address
in 6.1 with this philosophical question
well i think this basically summarizes
the point about dynamics mechanics and
principles that we were making earlier
um you know so the fep has been
described variously
in various and sometimes very different
ways even by like its core proponents so
carl uh introduced the fdp to the world
as a theory of cortical function circa
and then as a unified brain theory um in
2010 which
led a lot of people and i think not to
um
this is in bad faith it led a lot of
people to say well okay so this is a
theory
and so it should be making predictions
and therefore
it should be empirically verifiable uh
so i think you know the
the way that we talked about it led to a
lot of uh confusion and it's been
described as you know a framework
whatever that means by myself included
right
so meia koopa we called it the active
inference framework for a long time
without really being specific as to what
that meant we kind of meant all this
this cluster of results that kind of
agglomerate around the fep
raja and colleagues have called this a
trick
uh kind of like a variational auto
encoder trick in machine learning so
it's a it's a trick if you can write a
markov blanket for a system that you can
make you can write down a model that
looks as that says that the system looks
as if it's performing bayesian inference
it's also been called a physics a
physics of sentient systems a formal
ontology
um so the point is to say well everyone
is kind of right you know
these are all in some sense valid
assessments and mel is really the one
who clarified things initially i think
by distinguishing formal structures
from interpreted empirically evaluable
uh models
and
um yeah i think the first part here is
to say well we can make sense of this
model by appealing to this tripartite
distinction that we've outlined so by
distinguishing dynamics
or descriptions formal descriptions of
some behavior that we want to get to
mechanical theories that explain how
and principles that explain why and then
what we're calling i think empirical
applications uh which are basically uh
these formal models plus uh an
assignment or an interpretation or
evaluation of these models in terms of
the features of target systems that we
want to explain
um
yeah so when they're applied in that way
mechanical theories become empirical
theories uh as we write in the ordinary
sense
but yeah so hopefully this kind of
clarifies everything around
falsification how this thing is used and
importantly why this is just standard
physics i mean this isn't
this isn't all that spooky in terms of
the use of mathematics to make sense of
physically relevant aspects of our
universe
um
so that's what we were trying to do in
that
section great
really clear 6.1 it reads to me like
it's the tip of an iceberg with a nice
landing and take off strip and yes it's
a big iceberg but it is an iceberg and
there is
a tip that makes sense
6.2 on page 39
elon vital
and the fep
what does this french linguistics have
to do with the fep maxwell
well uh dalton might have some pretty
interesting remarks to make but just
briefly i mean um
i find it kind of ironic that uh you
know the people who are
most critical of fep right now like
folks from the inactive tradition and
folks from the ecological tradition
sometimes frame
their own research is trying to you know
struggle against dualism in some sense
but our belief is that they are
intrinsically dualistic
frameworks um so
elon vitale is a french term
with
vitalism i don't know
how familiar you are with like the
history of biology but before the 20th
century in the uh discovery of dna most
serious uh physicists believed in
something like aristotle's entire key so
like that you you had to have some kind
of physical mechanism for
propositiveness
and so ella guitar was this kind of
vital force that uh they believe the
vitalists believe animated living
systems
and differentiated them from non-living
systems like stones and rocks
and
we believe that one of the consequences
of the perspective that we're adopting
here and building on you know especially
the work of mike levin who's done
amazing uh
made amazing contributions in this field
is that it
self-organization and cognition and life
and these these things that we like to
point out as being distinct from inert
matter are actually are more on a
continuum
uh the you know the bayesian mechanic
says that um
basically anything that's a thing
will exhibit some features of what we
think of as cognition
um so uh it is a massive massively
deflationary and absolutely resolutely
monistic perspective that we're
advancing here
uh
yeah it was just you know
the um
trying to look for
the boundary between living and
non-living systems is bound to fail in
some sense
there is a continuum these processes
that we're interested in
are also evidenced by rocks and by
tornadoes and by crystals and it is a
question of degree
uh to which systems uh
act
as cognitive systems
um
yeah
i'm sure dalton has more interesting
things to say about that
yes on 6.2 what else would you add there
dalton well maybe not
more interesting perhaps more
interesting things to say
but uh
well yeah i mean i think this section is
is mostly just um
a recapitulation of footnote two in a
sense
um
meaning you know we we made this
statement
that inference
per se representation of some statistics
of something else
is this very broad very general thing
and any system that is not a closed
system does inference so what that means
is you know under the free energy
principle
and at least what we've written in that
paper was you know what we've worked out
so far
uh there isn't uh
a way to talk about cognition versus
non-cognition
it's more of a spectrum of cognition
there are certain systems that are more
competent this is something that carl
might call
a temporal depth so there are systems
that are very good at planning and
executing actions and there are systems
that are not you know so there's a very
clear difference between humans and
stones for instance but that difference
isn't in
one does inference and another doesn't
it's that one does a bit more
complicated inference it has uh
better or more accurate representations
or more representations full stop maybe
uh and it's better at using those
representations to to do action but both
stones and humans are estimators of the
statistics of the processes around them
simply by mathematical construction and
and so there's this very
uh
uncontroversial statement or at least it
shouldn't be a controversy that systems
things
in the very most general sense
exhibit this kind of
representation-based
inference that we would typically
identify
as cognition
so that was the motivation for talking
about that and then maxwell tied a very
nice bow on it with this uh this great
history of
a debate around
very similar questions uh but yeah it
was this idea of a spectrum of cognition
awesome and citation 92 there is the
2018 paper answering schrodinger's
question
so
many years ago
the other maxwell at all
who raised that question and sparked
really a phase transition in the
discourse and that was also like one of
those
it was one of the papers that really
drew me in
and got me excited and so it's amazing
to see
what other questions and answers have
been risen
6.3 and then g so 6.3 is a slightly
longer section
and it's on maps and territories so yeah
what is that i'm really glad i'm really
glad that we were able to
write this so
um
i i never found this particularly
confusing but i i i i it has led to a
lot of confusion
um so in particular there's this entire
paper by thomas van ness that just is
just confused about
uh
this issue uh i forget what it's called
as the
living
life modeled or
what anyway um
so
folks have said well so is is the free
energy principle um
just just a description
that we are uh you know
a model that we are using to describe
interesting features of the world or
is it saying that um
you know self-organizing systems
actually
are models
of the world
um
and
so you know
we
i never particularly
found this
problematic
um
because i so
the this phrase uh in in the paper i
think sums it up correctly uh
the free energy principle is in some
sense a map of that part of the
territory that looks as if
it is a map
um and so uh
thomas metzinger actually retweeted our
paper and pointed uh called this nested
representationalism which i found
interesting
so
yeah there are these kind of two
distinct levels at play
but there's no foul play here because
the
fep model is very explicit about
which parts of the formalism pertain to
our map of the territory and which parts
of the formalism pertain to
the map that self-organizing systems are
constructing according to our map
um yeah so i i i think it's important to
point out that you know there isn't a
contradiction here um that there are
just these two probability densities
that are at play in the construction the
q density and the p density and you can
understand the
the generative model or the p density
as basically uh our model of uh
the
self-organizing system in terms of uh
yeah joint probability density uh
over uh it's it's state space or
potentially it's a
space of paths
um so
in that sense you know um the
the
self-organizing system being its own
best model uh really means we have a
model uh we can explain the system's
dynamics and the the system's uh
potential uh is is formalized uh you
know as a as a generative model as a
joint probability density
it just so happens that part of the
variables that are described by that
joint probability density uh play the
role of parametrizing
additional
probability densities over another
subset
of variables described by the generative
model so there are really these two i
think
unambiguously different
senses of being a model that are at play
um
and
yeah
i don't think this is a sleight of hand
and hopefully we have clarified
yeah what
what exactly is at stake here um i think
there are some nice connections to the
maximum entropy uh formulation so as
dalton
articulated
in the paper at least uh
and no he you said you said as much in
discussion today um i think you
by by flipping to the perspective of uh
maximization of entropy we we
effectively recover our own position as
modelers trying to model the system
um so
the the the
prism through maximum entropy is uh adds
this additional clarification that uh
yeah we can entirely recover the
perspective of a model or using maximum
entropy modeling to model a free energy
type system by invoking this duality of
perspectives
and i think that's really important
[Music]
then there's this other piece here which
says that the
the maps that we construct in fep and in
max end uh both adhere to a kind of
epistemic minimalism
so maximum entropy inference is
basically uh saying i'm going to uh well
given some data set uh the uh
probability density that most that is uh
the one that best explains the data set
is the one with the highest entropy what
this means is that
we are uh building in to that uh
probability distribution as little prior
information as possible it's like
starting from the point of view of
maximal ignorance given a few
constraints what is the underlying
probability density
the fep has a similar you know starting
point for maximal ignorance which says i
can't go beyond the blanket like i i am
stuck with the data that i'm generating
and uh with the way that i probe the
world this data generating process to
generate my data and th there is no
going beyond that you can't go beyond
the blanket unless you break the blanket
but then you're just introducing a new
blanket so for example um you know i i
can't see in your brains um i could put
you in an fmri machine and break the
blanket but then i'm i'm really
introducing another
another blanket you know which is this
new set of data that i have to continue
making inferences from um
so
i mean the then the the fep and accent
kind of emerge as uh these
epistemically um
minimalistic or um
you know
they kind of emerge as the way that you
would construct a map of the part of the
territory that acts as a map from a
perspective from from a starting point
of maximal ignorance
great and i think that's connected in
the active inference textbook to figure
9.1
the meta bayesian perspective
and there it's not described in the
context of maximum entropy but it's
something very similar with this nested
representationalism on
any other philosophical notes before we
go to section seven
yeah that's exactly right
that's exactly right yeah yeah i love
this book
um yeah
is that anything to add before we launch
into g theory
no i think you raised an interesting
point um so we can talk about
you know
when we use the fep to model a system
what we're doing is
forming a model of the system where the
system forms a model of its environment
and so there is this nested
representationalism
what's interesting about the maximum
entropy point of view is you can um kind
of
uh dualize it you can you can take the
sort of mirror image of this thing and
you can ask okay well
we're not interested in a model of the
system modeling something all we want is
a model of the system so what does the
system look like when it's creating that
model not what does the system's model
look like
so this is this is the dualization
aspect of things and so you can talk
about and when you dualize you can talk
about things like constraints on agents
states
rather than the predictions and actions
of the agent so it's a bit of a
different viewpoint it's just
emphasizing
different
uh
levels of
the nest so to speak
um
which is which is kind of interesting
because you do get both of these
perspectives for free
as soon as you commit to this relational
symmetry of an observer in an
environment and an agent in an
environment and how those two things do
model each other
um and that's what you get when you
dualize things
uh but that's yeah that's that's it for
me on that section i think maxwell
pretty much covered uh a lot of the
important points
i i mean i i will say that you know this
this probably is not obvious
until you really look at the
mathematical formulation
uh and notice that there are two you
know as i as i wrote in that paper from
a few years ago the fep is a tale of two
densities
um and you really need to
uh like
take take a look at the math to
understand that there isn't a this isn't
like a case of reification
this is just formulated so it it it
isn't so simple that you could just put
it in a
direct and a simple graph and say hey
look here are these two
uh
but definitely if you take the time to
work through the um
the formalism
there are clearly these two different
senses of uh being a model that are at
play um
that are cleanly distinguished and i
think are actually not all that
problematic
awesome it's almost like thinking
through other minds highlighted some of
the social consequence and theory of
mind and behavioral aspects of certain
types of cognitive entities but systems
thinking of through about other systems
or infers thinking through other infers
infra ants
that type of dual view from the inside
view from the outside is again what
you're suggesting is enabled by that
kind of a commitment to these
foundations
and
of course it could be a whole other
guest stream and perhaps should be on g
theory
but as we close here what can we say
today on
613 2022
about g theory and what is exciting you
all about how you're going to continue
forward
do you want to take this one dalton
uh yeah sure uh so
i mean like i mentioned earlier on um
there's already a lot of really
promising stuff in the literature about
patented girls and path entropy
and the kind of power it has to deal
with
systems that we would uh normally kind
of balk at and
and so it's it's already very promising
there's reason to be optimistic about
how this extension will benefit us in
the future
um
so g theory itself is is um
maxwell coined this term to describe the
uh extension of this duality from
mode matching and accent max cal
which will involve um precisely this
we'll try to formulate um the free
energy principle in its full generality
as dual to uh entropy in its full
generality on paths and so forth um
and and so
the reason why this is so exciting is
because already there's a very clear
path towards talking about um systems
that are non-stationary so systems whose
statistics change more complicated forms
of inference uh more complicated forms
of constraints and preferences
and so it seems like already it's a much
more faithful description of the kinds
of systems that we want to talk about
and extends to things like um
more complex systems uh things like
humans potentially um
so so this is really the uh
i guess the the end goal is to do this
dualization to now build
an fep dual model of something like a
brain which we know models its
environment in this very complicated way
and so the kinds of representations it
does are very complicated so how do we
model that
um
that that should uh arise out of maximum
caliber and and therefore out of g
theory
and in principle you know eventually
we'll have a very faithful uh very
foundational picture of complex systems
but this is a very um long-term goal
in the short term we just want to get
the maths to work
to connect that a bit to lars's uh
question earlier uh what does it mean to
have a non-stationary density over paths
well i mean what we're interested in is
the way that the density changes as a
function of the dynamics so that you
really have like these moving surfaces
over a space of paths or space of states
and to really capture all of that kind
of time dependency
uh
yeah requires moving from uh accent to
maxcal uh from states to paths
and um
all of these kind of more fine-grained
uh
you know
wandering blankets and moving attractors
and all of that good stuff
should fall
fairly naturally out of
yeah g theoretic formulation of this
stuff
i like how within fep as we know it we
have variational free energy f and then
expected free energy takes us into the
future and planning and that's g and
then we see a little bit of like free
energy principal f and then g is the
next letter so that's a funny little
would know duel
analogy um
well
if anybody has any closing thoughts it
would be a great time for that but just
wanted to say that there's a lot of
appreciation in the chat and a lot of
excitement around this work so we hope
that you just
continue
acting and inferring and serving
that's that's kind of you to say uh
yeah thank you very much for the
invitation to discuss our work
this has been great uh and yeah we uh we
look forward to uh you know exploring
the future uh with this whole community
and um thanks for your time your
attention your energy
uh
very very positive always a pleasure to
be on actin flab
and uh yeah thanks for the guest stream
yes i can only echo that uh it's been a
pleasure so thank you
thank you thank you maxwell and dalton
at all thank you lars for joining and
until the next time
bye
may the gradient descend ever in your
favor my friend
and with yours slash ours
bye
take care